<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copy of the queenes highnes co[m]mission</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1571</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116445</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851661</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851661</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21750)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 564:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copy of the queenes highnes co[m]mission</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1571</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Powles Churchyarde, by Richarde Iugge, printer to the Queenes Maiestie. Cum priuilegio regiæ maiestatis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1572?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Appoints commissioners to enforce the requirement that men children be provided with bows and arrows and that no person is to keep for gain any place in which unlawful games are played.</note>
                  <note>Last complete line of text ends: "witnesse"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Archery --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16947:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>The copy of the queenes highnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>LIZABETH</hi> by the grace of God, Queene of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland, defender of the faith. &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>To our truſtie &amp; welbeloued A.B.C.D. and to euery of you, greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas in the Parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxxiii. yeere of the raigne of our late deare Father of woorthy memory kyng Henry the eyght, one acte or ſtatute was then and there made, for the mayntenance of Artillerie, and debarring of vnlawful games. By the whiche good ſtatute, amongeſt many other thynges, it was prouided, that the Fathers, Gouernours, and Maiſters of the youth of this our Realme, ſhoulde in diuers and ſundry ſortes trayne and bring vp theyr youth in ſhooting in the long bowe, and ſhould haue for that purpoſe ſeueral bowes and arrowes, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and quantitie accordying to theyr ages and yeeres, vpon ſuche payne and penaltie as is expreſſed in the ſayde ſtatute, as by the ſame ſtatute more at large it doth and may appeare. And being geuen to vnderſtand, that for lacke of due ſearche whether euery perſon and perſons haue bowe and arrowes, accordyng to the tenour of the ſayd acte, the commendable exerciſe &amp; vſe of ſhooting, and the reſt of the good deuiſes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions conteyned in the ſayde ſtatute, is therefore in the moſt partes of this our Realme vtterly forgotten, and not accompliſhed. And to thentent that ſhooting may be vſed and exerciſed within this our Realme as in tymes paſt, and vnlawful games ſuppreſſed and put out of vſe, we haue thought it conuenient for good conſyderations vs ſpecially mouyng, to nominate, aſſigne, and appoynt you to be our Commiſſioners, geuyng vnto you and euery of you, and to al other officers aucthoriſed by the ſayde ſtatute, ful power and aucthoritie by vertue of theſe preſentes, in our name, not only from tyme to tyme as often as neede ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, to make due and lawful ſearche in euery place within our Countie of S. aſwel within liberties as without, aſwel for ſuche as vſe vnlawful games, as alſo for ſuche as kepe houſes or alleys for vnlawful games: but alſo whether euery perſon for hym ſelfe, his ſeruantes, and other youth in his or theyr ſeuerall houſes, haue ſufficient furniture and prouiſion of bowe and arrowes, and haue and do vſe and occupie the ſame, accordyng to the true meanyng of the ſayde ſtatute.</p>
            <p>And to thend the ſame may be the better vnderſtanded and knowen, our pleaſure and commaundement is, that al ſuche bowes and arrowes that euery perſon ought to haue by the order of the ſayde ſtatute, ye ſhal cauſe the parties to bryng to ſome conuenient place or places, within the pariſhe where ſuch parties dwell, by the diſcretion of you our ſayd Commiſſioners, or any of you, there to be viewed and ſeene by you our ſayd Commiſſioners, or any of you. Vpon whiche ſearche, viewe, and examination, yf you or any of you our ſaid Commiſſioners, or any other our officer aboueſayde, ſhal finde any perſon or perſons, eyther not furniſhed with bowe and arrowes, or not vſyng the ſame, as by the ſayd ſtatute is limitted and appoynted, or any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons vſing vnlawful games, or keeping houſes or alleyes for vnlawful games, contrary to the meanyng of the ſayde ſtatute: that then our pleaſure is, that you our ſayde Commiſſioners, and euery of you, by gentle admonition ſhal do your good endeuour to cauſe a reformation to be had therein, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of ſhoting may be vſed and continued by as many of our good ſubiectes of euery eſtate, as can or may vſe the ſame. And yf you can not by gentle admonition and order, cauſe the offendours to refourme them ſelues in the premiſſes: then our pleaſure is alſo that you, or any two of you, ſhal cauſe the names and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng places of ſuche offendours to be noted and certified vnto the Lorde Chauncelour, or Lorde keper of the great ſeale of Englande for the tyme beyng, to thintent we may cauſe ſuche order and direction to be taken and had therein, as by the lawes and ſtatutes of this our Realme is prouided in that behalfe. Wherefore we wyl and commaunde al and ſinguler our officers, miniſters, and ſubiectes of our ſayde Countie, aſwel within the liberties, as without, that they and euery of them be aydyng, helpyng, and aſſiſtyng you our ſaid Commiſſioners, and euery of you, in the due execution of this our Commiſſion, as they and euery of them tender our pleaſure, and wyl anſwere for the contrary at theyr perils. In witnes whereof. &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Witneſſe our ſelfe. &amp;c.</dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London in Powles <hi>Churchyarde, by Richarde Iugge, printer to the</hi> Queenes Maieſtie.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
